the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet review of
holography
[Music]
hello this is Frankie greatest and
welcome to holotalk the internet laser
and holography talk show our toll-free
number is
1-800-458-3525 or you can send an email
to holotalk
poloworld.com we've got telephone calls
we've got emails we've got special
guests coming up so thank you for tuning
in and let's get this week's show on the
road
okay everyone welcome once again to
another week of holotalk this is Frankie
Freitas your host
I am death on toast this week
finding that blue bug that was going
around for a couple weeks and everything
seemed fine and all of a sudden I got
hit with bronchitis so I hope you bear
with me
so we get this show together and get it
out to you
still running a fever 102 so bear with
me please
I'd like to make a few announcements on
our guests which are coming up in the
next few weeks next week which is going
to be January 18th Our Guest is going to
be Dr Stephen Benton who is the head of
the spatial Imaging group at the media
lab at MIT
Dr Benton's going to fill us in on
what's going to be happening out at spie
the conference out on the west coast and
we'll also be talking with Dr Benton on
General holographic issues as well on
February 1st we're seeing Brian Monahan
Brian is from a company called
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper and they are
actually famous for doing the Men in
Black video
cassette cover so if you've seen the Men
in Black video on the shelves that is
the company that created that and
they're going to be featured in the
Philadelphia Inquirer
on Monday so if you're listening to this
on Sunday or you're listening to it on
Monday check the Philadelphia Inquirer
and you're going to see a article on
Pennsylvania paulton paper the musical
guest for these two weeks the musical
guests with Dr Stephen Benton will be
Julie Moffett and the musical guest with
Brian Monahan will be Brazil 2000.
the
the light craft if you remember we
covered a topic called lightcraft
technology a few weeks ago where the Air
Force is working with a number of
different
organizations and producing this
microsatellite launch system that uses
Pulses from a laser to put it into orbit
this this vehicle actually Rises on a
pulsed laser beam I was contacted by the
people of light craft the researchers
themselves out it I believe it was
Edwards Air Force Base
and they said they'd like to do a
special interview on Hollow talk about
lightcraft technology so I've returned
their call and I'll probably hear from
them early next week and we'll set up a
date now Hollow talk is booked until
1999. I've I've closed off all bookings
at the end of 98.
um so we're booked totally for the year
so what I'm going to do with the light
craft people because from what I
understand they have some very exciting
tests that are coming up for them
they're going to actually test a larger
vehicle using this technology Sometime
Late spring early summer so I'd like to
get them on and I'm going to put them on
one of the middle weeks like this week
where we don't have a scheduled guest
and we'll hear what they're doing with
light craft technology this is very
exciting I I find this almost science
fiction come true you know we all sit
down and we hear about all these science
fiction topics and all these things that
are possible to do in science fiction
and rarely
do we see something happen in our
lifetime that can truly be
considered a science fiction dream come
true I've seen a few videos of this
technology and this craft actually just
Rises right up on the laser beam it's so
cool so we'll have to make sure that we
get some of the streaming video up again
also so we're going to arrange to have
the light craft people come on as soon
as possible
okay we're going to move on to a couple
questions actually we got quite a few
questions in this week uh for holo talk
and I'm going to answer them in the
order that they were received some
people signed them some people didn't
and if you do sign them I'll use your
first name it was our policy when we
started the show last year not to use
anyone's name on the air but I guess it
would be okay to use the first name and
we'll see how that works out if we get
anyone that writes in and says you know
you used my name I wish you wouldn't do
that we'll go back to not using the name
again but we won't use the last name
we'll just use the first name if someone
signs the email we have an interview
coming up a friend of mine who goes to
the I don't know see this medication's
got me so that I can't think School of
Visual Arts in New York City and she's a
studying photography and computer
Graphics there she came back home to the
Lehigh Valley over the holiday and she
stopped in and we did an interview with
her from a student's College student's
perspective on holography and she's
going to fill us in on some of the
things that she feels about holography
and also a reaction that she got to
several other students and faculty
members when she suggested that they try
to work holography in into the school
um I believe they already have a
holography program at the center for
visual arts center of Visual Arts in New
York
let's go on to the uh to a couple
questions and then we'll get with the
interview of the Lisa gold Farm is her
name
here's our first question my question is
about the content of the show when you
first started it it was mostly about
answering your listener's email and
going over some interesting facts about
hologography but lately I haven't heard
any emails don't get me wrong some of
the interviews you're doing are
interesting and I know you probably need
the sponsoring but it seems you've lost
your original purpose and there's a
question mark there and this was sent in
by Scott well Scott
um there were a couple shows where we
didn't get as many emails and what we
wanted to do was the weeks that we were
doing the interview we wanted to spend a
little bit more time on the interviews
and less on the emails and then in the
middle weeks go to the emails themselves
um you said you find the interviews
interesting and I thank you for that and
you say you probably need to sponsoring
well the people who come on the show for
interviews to not sponsor this show the
show is not sponsored by the guests I I
sponsor the show I pay for this when you
hear someone being interviewed on this
show no matter where that phone call was
made I pay for that phone call so
um it's not like someone sponsors a
specific show and then they get to come
on the show as a guest but I I thank you
for this and uh hopefully you'll see the
pattern that emerges from this we will
probably change shows from time to time
I do want to try and leave some room for
Change and experimentation with the
different things that we do on the show
but um
I hope that answers your question on
that the next question was sent in by
Julie and she writes in what different
effects does the power level of your
laser have on the image you create
well Julie
um
film has a certain sensitivity to it and
you have to hit that emotion with a
certain amount of energy per square
centimeter in order to really nail that
exposure so that leaves us with a number
of different problems number one we have
when you have a very low power laser you
can still accumulate that power but it's
over a longer period of time and you're
out of that sensitivity curve of the
Emulsion The Perfect Exposure is when
you can hit that Emulsion with the exact
energy over time
that that emotion requires and sometimes
that calls for a very powerful laser a
number of different things also with a
higher power laser your exposure times
are short and the reason that that's
important is because it cuts down any
chance of having any creep coming into
the system which will make your hologram
dimmer
you just get better results with the
higher power lasers than you do a lower
power laser but you know I've done some
very nice Holograms using five
milliwatts laser five milliwatt helium
neon lasers I've done multiple color
Holograms using five milliwatt lasers
using the triathanolamine technique
where you pre-sensitize and pre-swell
the Emulsion before each exposure these
weren't large commercial type Holograms
you'd find in a Convention Center I
worked basically with four by five inch
glass plates but they turned out very
nice and it's just using five moons I
think right now if with the new
emulsions that we're starting to see
that require quite a bit more energy per
exposure that it's certainly to your
advantage to have as much power as
possible available to you to work with
on the
in your system
okay uh our next email question
doesn't have a name
I'm hearing rumors of a Super Bowl
commercial using some type of hologram
that may win the best of show award have
you heard anything thanks no I haven't
heard anything at all perhaps
one of our listeners could write in and
tell us a little about this
okay this is someone who's writing and
saying there's a Super Bowl commercial
using some type of hologram
keep in mind that if they're using a
hologram it's just going to be a flat
image on your screen because your
screen's not capable showing a
three-dimensional images
which a lot of people don't seem to
understand especially with computers and
things and they expect that they can see
a three-dimensional hologram on their
computer monitors and things just
because it happens to be a picture of a
hologram but the picture itself is
actually two-dimensional
so no I haven't heard anything about
this
very interesting uh interesting seeing
what this is so if any of our listeners
have any idea what company or what the
story is behind a commercial that's
going to be using Holograms
during the Super Bowl uh please write to
Homeworld I just want to let you know
that you can send your questions in
either by email or call them in although
email seems to be the way of choice
we're not getting any phone calls so
that's fine I mean it doesn't matter to
me which way the questions come in the
email address is Holo talk
at holerworld.com and there's several
links and even a form available right on
the whole talk page where you can send
your question or you can call in and
we'll use your voice on mail on the air
which is
1-800-458-3525 and once again I
apologize for being a little bit off
this week I am right at the peak of a
bronchitis infection and between the
antibiotics and the codeine I think it's
really affecting my head
probably by the end of the week when I'm
feeling better I'll log on and listen to
this about just cringe but the show must
go on all right we have an interview
coming up this young lady her name is
Lisa Goldfarb and she attends the School
of Visual Arts in New York and she
stopped in the studio she's interested
in holography quite a bit as a art
medium using it for ways of expression
and being creative with it and we just
did a quick interview with her so we're
going to go to the Lisa gold Farm
interview and I have not edited anything
this week I am sending everything up as
is and I record this stuff
in bits and pieces and then I put them
together and normally what I do is I go
in and I edit it down nicely but I'm not
doing that this week so you're seeing
you're hearing everything
the way that it was recorded mistakes
and everything is linked
okay they're coming into the studio now
they have absolutely no idea they're
going to be on the air so they should be
coming around to the stairs in just a
second
okay
I see four feet
looks like she brought protection
this is a rough neighborhood folks so
you have to bring protection when you
come to the studio here hello Lisa how
are you
why don't you pick up the chair and grab
a seat at that microphone for a second
everyone's dying to hear what you have
to say
oh no she says
swinging around turn your mic on
there you go let me tell you how this
works you speak loudly and clearly into
the microphone like I am like this yes
and people will be able to understand
you that's how it works I don't know
people usually don't understand me
anyway
Lisa goes to school at the school for
visual arts Visual Arts School of Visual
Arts in the Big Apple
SVA okay
what I'd like to have you say to the
people that listen to the show as an
artist well why don't you tell people
what it is you're studying
move up close to the mic now see every
people getting like people get Mike shy
you know people love to have their
picture taken they love videos but the
minute they come up to a mic they stall
so go ahead get up to the mic tell
people what you what it is you study
school for photography and
really okay which means it's photography
and related media
mixed media Digital Imaging so you get a
chance to work on the computers too you
work a lot on computers try to
synthesize them all somehow into art
Photoshop Photoshop Quark okay
the internet the internet for doing
websites
now
we met about a year ago right
yeah yeah May and you were interested in
holography
in that year's time why don't you tell
the folks what you've found out about
hologography and some of your ideas on
it
um you've seen a couple shows at the
center right yeah okay I think we had a
show there that were random Holograms I
think some of the Holograms were the
portraits from Richmond holographics in
England
along with some work from Greg cherry
and things of that type of a show and
then we bought the show in from Ukraine
I think you were there to see a Ukraine
show and now you were there which we
have a lot of the the show that we have
at the center right now is uh holography
in the real world which is showing
Holograms uh packaging advertising
things of that nature
what's what's your scoop on holography
where it's at right now as just your own
personal opinion doesn't have to be
anything that's been sent down from the
clouds or anything like that just what
you think about it
well so far all I've seen of holography
is uh
and it hasn't been art yet I've seen I
think it may solve
seen one uh holography our exhibit and I
was quite a while ago do you remember
where that was Moravian College oh okay
we had uh that wasn't the one that was
there like in the last two years or
something was it yeah oh okay yeah that
was a traveling uh exhibit that one in
there yeah you thought that was pretty
cool yeah
can't really talk about it right now but
you don't remember a lot from it no no
well see that that's an indication of
something too
right my rapid memory loss no I mean as
far as the content of the show
well I mean
um
can use a holography other than just
representing an object
so in other words instead of just
building a sculpture of something and
then doing a hologram of the sculpture
you'd rather see holography used where
it's a medium unto itself where the
field of Photography itself is actually
used to express some form of creativity
rather than just trying to copy already
existing objects right I mean
photography similar to that too I mean
you can
you know just be a
you know just take someone's picture you
know the blue background behind it for
the family
or you can make an exciting portrait do
you think
do you think computers are expanding
your creativity with photography or are
they just taking the place of
traditional ways of doing things in the
dark room yeah yeah so far they're just
speeding up the process just speeding up
the process do you yourself remember
many students that are in that course
that are actually doing things that you
would not be able to do in a doctoring
situation
not not yet so in other words using
computers for photography is similar to
the same results that we're seeing with
holography where it's just being an
extension of already known things and
ways of doing things rather than using
it specific for itself yeah because
there are there are some effects
but you could never get with traditional
Optics and things right not that I've
seen like like that image you have on
your desktop
that would be tough with traditional
photography to do that right yeah yeah
with that program that takes me about
three minutes yeah
yeah I mean
I mean a lot of things you can't do with
traditional darkroom methods because it
takes so long to do all the layering to
use all those effects because it takes
so long
the computer needs to do the calculation
time yeah okay
so that's that's more a uh collecting uh
quicker and
faster realized so what about with
holography what would you like to see as
an artist happen
with holography what would you like to
see that you would be able to look at
and say you know this is really a very
creative use of this field
um I'm still working on that one I'm
still working I think everybody is
yeah
I mean I haven't haven't worked so much
with holography so I'm not really I
don't know all the
internet is how to do it
yeah
what could could really be done or what
could be tweaked here and there to
do some pretty interesting facts the
reason why I have you on here is because
you seem like you're really interested
in it you're bright
and uh
maybe we can get something out of you
you know it'd be wonderful now they have
a holography program at your school
and I'm not quite sure if the same
person's still running it but it may be
the program that's run by Doris villant
she's a very well-known holographer and
does beautiful work you know so look her
up when you go back to instead of
hanging around with a loser like me you
know you never get anywhere with me
you're not a loser Frank
well every so often I like to bring
somebody on the air so that you know
people listen across the country and
around the world actually they listen to
this in China and everything and
just to get you know another perspective
from someone I don't want to say off the
street but you're not in like the field
itself of philosophy because if I put a
holographer in here you know they could
chew the fact for hours on how wonderful
things are and you know the deep meaning
of all the things that they've done with
holography but it's the person on the
street picking up on that or not you
know that's that's the whole thing I
like to find out sometimes yeah I mean
even when I I mentioned holography to
some of the students at my program they
they kind of shrug it off and really
they said oh that won't really fly with
our chairman of art so he won't be
brilliant to that isn't that something
do you think the reason for that is they
don't consider it a viable medium for
expression because it's a nice school
because all they've seen of it as just
representing an object they haven't seen
it yeah see what it can do that's why I
think it's exciting I mean that's new
it's fresh yeah and everything goes
through that when it's new too you know
photography actually went through that
right you know they still be going
through it I don't know if they've ever
yes you know I don't think
people consider photography art yet or
they're just starting to which is really
crazy because I imagine but it's not
always art so traditional photography
has got to be pretty close to uh
I wouldn't say being phased out but
being replaced by other things
so it's possible the holography may have
gone through its entire history from
conception to the point where it's ready
to pass the torch to something else
without really finding its place in art
kind of like the theremin
that was a musical instrument right yeah
what was the Thurman I remember that I
was like from back in the early 70s or
something wasn't it yeah was it a ribbon
or something or what no this
it was like the precursor to the uh
synthesizer okay I think
I'm not exactly sure how how it worked
but
um something to do with the
wave the
I see
Heather technology technology actually I
think that things but I guess right
because technologists just took over too
quickly about something better yeah all
right well
I grabbed you right away
it's for the shock value of walking into
something and walking into a radio thing
so
um I want to thank you for at least you
know not getting mad at me but who knows
what happened when we turn the mic off
right all right so we'll get you guys
some coffee or something and then we'll
uh we'll talk shop and stuff
So Lisa thanks for being on thanks for
having me okay
bye okay we'll get back to the older
part of the show
okay that's Lisa go farm interview let's
move on we're going to um I want to
thank Lisa for coming in and doing that
that was really off the cuff so uh it
was nice of her to give us a little bit
of a perspective a student a college
student perspective on holography
here we have another question let me
read the question I am just about to
build the sand slab table described in
the holography handbook
and I remember reading
to stay away from building tables with
too many layers of crap
um vibration is not a problem as long as
the optical components are all anchored
securely and thus vibrate together what
do you recommend
um I worked with the holography
handbooks fan and slab table for many
years and you know it was it's a great
table
it is true
that it's not so much vibration that it
is the fact that everything's vibrating
together you could take that table and
vibrate the living heck out of it
and as long as everything on that table
was vibrating uniformly
in relationship to one another you could
still do a hologram
it's when things vibrate out of phase on
that table
that's when you have your problem
and that's more of an issue of stiffness
and rigidity than it is vibration
isolation
now I've seen a few tables that were not
very stiff
and if you pressed on one of the ends
instead of the table moving uniformly
which means the other end coming up
proportionately with you putting the
energy on the other end of the table
pushing down the table bends
now that's a problem
now if you have a table where you can
press on one end and the opposite end of
the table comes up and that table stays
very rigid and stiff then you're fine
so this is true
um sometimes vibration isn't actually
the problem as much as it is how well
that's that table is the stiffness of
that table and the rigidity of the table
um the second part of the question here
is what coherence length should I look
for in a helium neon laser this is a d
question and is it worth the extra money
to buy one that is greater than 30
milliwatts
well all helium neon lasers I think up
until the point where you get to the
spectrophysics I believe it's 125. has
has a very long coherence length
I believe the 125 to get a long coherent
you need to use an addition called
an edelon
but um
most helium neon lasers are going to
give you the amount of coherence length
that you're going to need to do your
hologram
I believe it's true that the higher
power the higher you get in the power
range that the less coherence length is
there but I think coherence length
generally is proportional to the length
of the tube
so I don't think you're going to find a
helium neon laser it's going to give you
such a short coherence not that you're
not going to be able to do good
Holograms with it and remember your
coherent coherence length excuse me
uh is really only going to come into
play when you're doing something like a
laser transmission hologram anyway which
is capable of showing quite a bit of
depth your your transmission hold your
white light transmission Holograms also
can show quite a bit of depth but if
you're going to be doing reflection
Holograms you're pretty much limited to
how much depth away either in front of
or behind the uh the image plane itself
the plate itself you can go so I think
any helium neon laser that you choose is
going to give you plenty of coherence
length to do what type of holograms
you're interested in doing
okay folks that about wraps it up for
another week
just as reminders on January 18th that's
coming up next week our special guest is
going to be Dr Stephen Benton
head of the spatial Imaging group the
media lab at MIT
and February 1st
Brian Monahan from Pennsylvania Pulp and
Paper and they're the company that
produced the Men in Black video cassette
boxes
and if you live in the Philadelphia area
the tri-state area down Southeastern
Pennsylvania you want to look into the
Philadelphia Inquirer on Monday because
there's a special story about
Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper in the paper
that day
also we're going to have a
representative from Edwards Air Support
space come on the show and give us an
interview about lightcraft technology
I'll have more information on the exact
data that when we close something out on
that and get some confirmation so this
is Frankie Freitas
I got through this show I want to thank
you very much for tuning in and my
apologies again for not being quite up
to Snuff as they say
I tried my best to get this show
together for you so at least when you
log on you're not going to hear a repeat
show so thank you very much for tuning
in and I look forward to having you tune
in next week for the Steve Benton
interview take care